人Ky免一死？
Must we die?
宇宙中有]有L生不死的生物
Are there beings in the cosmos who live forever...
可以永h逍b地游在rg之河上？
afloat on an endless journey down the river of time?
宇宙大探索
第十一集
我的先祖依靠的是月亮c星星rg分段r
Our ancestors marked the passage of time by the Moon and stars.
可在大s5000年前 在@Y生活^的人
But it was the people who once lived here, around 5,000 years ago,
他_始把rg分
who first starting chopping up time
小r和分@痈小的部分
into smaller bite-sized portions of hours and minutes.
r@地方叫做豸克
They call this place Uruk.
我F在Q之橐晾克
We call it Iraq.
@Y是位於底格里斯河c幼l拉底河之g
It's a part of Mesopotamia,
美索不_米平原的一部分
the land between the Tigris and the Euphrates rivers.
人在@Y建了城市
The city was invented here.
在crgoM的痿Y中
And one of humanity's greatest victories was won
取得了人v史上一ゴ蟮某删
in the ceaseless battle against time.
人在@YW了如何
It was here that we learned how to write.
死亡再也不能人默默o
Death could no longer silence us.
o予了人力量
And writing gave us the power
我可以逾越千年
to reach across the millennia
c古人交流精神
and speak inside the heads of the living.
v史上]有人
No one has ever spoken
能穿越如此之L的rg之河
across a longer stretch of time's river
除了阿卡德帝的公主
than this Akkadian princess,
她是v史上第一位君王的女
daughter of the first emperor in history,
也被Q樵铝凉主――恩西杜安娜
and priestess of the Moon-- Enheduanna.
她不HH歌
For not only did she write poetry,
恩西杜安娜做了其他一些
but Enheduanna did something
前人]有做^的事情
no one before her had ever done--
她在作品上署上自己的名字
she signed her name to her work.
可以f 她是v史上第一
She's the first person for whom we can say
我知道_切身份
we know who she was,
也知道她的粝胧澜绲娜
and what she dreamed.
她一直粝胫能走M神奇之T
She dreamt of stepping through the Gate of Wonder.
@就是恩西杜安娜所想
Here's a thought Enheduanna sent
它穿越了4000年的r光淼轿身
across more than 4,000 years to you.
下面就是她的作品
It's from her work entitled
名椤缎∨雄心》
Lady of the Largest Heart.
英娜娜 天上的金星
Innana, the planet Venus,
鄣呐神
goddess of love, will have a great destiny
你是宇宙ゴ蟮闹髟
throughout the entire universe.
宇宙的主宰
...throughout the entire universe.
豸克也是史
And Uruk is also the place where the epic tale
《英雄的旅程》首次作的地方
of "The Hero's Journey" was first written down.
h在蝙蝠b 天行者R克
Before Batman, Luke Skywalker,
W德――@些英雄Q生之前
Odysseus-- before them all--
髡f有一人叫吉伽美什
there was a man named Gilgamesh
他榱四苷鞣rg而hx了家l
who left home on a quest to vanquish time.
吉伽美什ひ著L生不死的方法
Gilgamesh was searching for immortality.
他走遍四方
He looked everywhere,
@得了o上的智慧
gained complete wisdom,
lF了[藏的秘密
uncovered what was hidden.
他е一堆大洪水r代之前的髌婊氐搅思亦l
He brought back a tale of times before the Great Flood.
他建造了後世的君王]有能c他媲美的豸克城池
He built the Wall of Uruk, which no future king will ever match.
吉伽美什的故事
Read the story of that man Gilgamesh,
描述了一在豸克Q生的英雄
a hero born of Uruk,
他v了千辛f苦
who went through all kinds of sufferings.
h渡重洋
Who crossed the ocean,
去到太升起的地方
the broad seas, as far as the sunrise;
世界的M^
who inspected the edges of the world,
只榱ひ永生的W秘
searching for eternal life.
在旅途中
On his travels,
吉伽美什遇到了一位名跆丶Gilgamesh encountered a wise man named Utnapishtim,
智者告V了他大洪水曾把世界
who told him the story of a flood that destroyed the world,
一位神明指示跆丶and how one of the gods instructed Utnapishtim
造出方舟 拯救他的家人c游
to build an ark to rescue his family and the animals.
@就是世界上最早的P於大洪水的髡f
The earliest surviving account of the flood legend
它a生於美索不_米
was written down in Mesopotamia,
直到1000年後
a thousand years before it was retold
《}・fs》中才出FZ方舟的故事
as the story of Noah in the Old Testament.
可以@Nf
So, you could say Gilgamesh
吉伽美什AM地完成了他τ郎的追求
fulfilled his quest for immortality.
@就是今天的《吉伽美什史》
We still read the Epic of Gilgamesh,
人每x一次 他就再生一次
and with every reader, he lives again.
自娜祟第一部英雄史Q生以
And all those heroes and superheroes who have come since
v史上涌F出o档挠⑿叟c超英雄
follow in the footsteps of the first hero's journey--
@可被槟撤N形式的永生
another kind of immortality;
S人文明而流鞯墓适
a story sent from one civilization to another
跨越千年
across thousands of years.
但生命本身也有自己的故事
But life itself sends its own stories
流髁撕装偃f年
across billions of years.
它就是我每人w榷yУ男畔
It's a message that every one of us carries inside,
烙印在我的胞之中
inscribed in all the cells of our bodies,
它用地球上的生命都知缘恼Z言
in a language that all life on Earth can read.
基因的密a表上
The genetic code is written in an alphabet
只有4字母
consisting of only four letters.
每字母代表著由原子M成的一分子
Each letter is a molecule made of atoms;
每卧~由3字母M成
each word is three letters long.
每生命都是了不起的茏
Every living thing is a masterpiece,
由自然 M化所
written by nature and edited by evolution;
它的\行c}u
the instructions for running and reproducing
由精密的生命C器所操v
the intricate machinery of life.
生命的基本信息
The essential message of life
已被反覆}u了3百f年
has been copied and recopied for more than 3 billion years.
但@些信息暮味恚
But where did that message come from?
o人知
Nobody knows.
也S它就Q生於@右光照射的\水塘
Perhaps it began in a shallow, sunlit pool, just like this.
不知何r起
Somehow, carbon-rich molecules
富碳分子_始使用能量ψ陨磉M行粗陋的}u
began using energy to make crude copies of themselves.
某些分子w具有更好的}u能力
Some varieties were better at making copies,
K留下了更多的後代
and left more offspring.
分子g的它得日益精巧
The competing molecules became more elaborate.
M化c生命由此悄然而生
Evolution and life itself was underway.
或S 生命是源於
Or life could've started
灼岬幕鹕娇谶上
in the searing heat of a volcanic vent
深藏於海底
on the deep sea floor.
甚至有]有可能 生命是搭著L自天而降
Or is it possible that life came to Earth
淼降厍虻哪
as a hitchhiker?
我砀你f故事
Let me tell you a story
P於另一世界的旅行者的故事
about a traveler from another world.
在v山大附近有一o的埃及小村f
The peace of the Egyptian village of Nakhla,
叫near Alexandria,
在1911年6月的某清晨 突然天降E
was abruptly shattered on a June morning in 1911.
在@KE石上d著
Written in this meteorite was
碜粤硪星球的信息
a message from another planet.
但直到70年後
But 70 years would pass
人才懂得如何解x
before anyone could read it.
1976年
In 1976,
美航天局伤揖S京探y器送上了火星
NASA landed two Viking spacecraft on Mars.
卡・_根把我引向那Y
Carl Sagan took us there
在人探索宇宙的早期
on our original journey through the cosmos.
我lF火星的大
We found that the Martian air
比地球稀薄
was less than one percent as dense as ours,
大部分由二氧化碳M成
and made mostly of carbon dioxide.
有小部分的氮
There were smaller amounts of nitrogen,
水蒸馀c氧
argon, water vapor and oxygen.
啄赆
A few years later,
科W家想要分析
when scientists thought to analyze the gasses
trapped inside the Nakhla meteorite,
c及其它的物|成分r
and other members of its class,
他lF了@人的相似性
they found a striking similarity--
大部分的E石
the vast majority of meteorites
是小行星的碎片
are fragments of asteroids.
但落在地球上的@KBut the kind that hit Nakhla, on Earth,
只有可能碜砸地方……
could only have come from one place...
那就是火星
Mars.
g迎淼交鹦
Welcome to Mars.
十|年前 @Y的一座火山爆l了
Over a billion years ago, a volcano erupted here
岩and its lava cooled into solid rock.
装偃f年後
Hundreds of millions of years later,
@K地方被洪水所淹]
this area was flooded with water.
洪水^後很多年
And long after that flood,
一K有直布_佗岩石那N大的小行星
an asteroid the size of the Rock of Gibraltar
撞袅嘶鹦潜砻
crashed into the Martian surface,
炸出一大坑
blasting out a huge crater.
大部分的碎片被到太空
Much of the debris was ejected back out into space,
碎片一_始@著太旋D
where it orbited the Sun until a gravitational tug
直到碜曰鹦堑囊力把其中一石K
from its home planet, Mars, diverted one of the boulders
D向c地球碰撞的道
into a collision course with Earth.
它最K抵_了Its arrival shook up the little village of Nakhla.
像Meteorites of the type that hit Nakhla
就是星Hg天然的\系y
are the vehicles of a natural interplanetary transit system
它在行星之g送石K
that sends rocks between the planets.
像@拥碾E石可以把微小的"物"安全\抵目的地
Such a meteorite can safely shelter microscopic cargo--
那就是生命的N子
the seeds of life--
它就是星H方舟
an interplanetary ark.
大部分的岩石是多孔的 有小的角落和p隙
Most rocks are porous, full of tiny nooks and crannies,
很m合生命用硗刀
where life can stow away.
我已lF好追N微生物
We know that some microbes can survive
能在毫拥奶空h境下生存
the hostile environment of space.
比如f 像@些小夥伴
Take these guys, for instance.
@些微生物
These microbes spent a year and a half riding
在H空g站外放置了一年半
on the outside of the International Space Station,
它暴露在O端的囟扰c真空下
exposed to the extreme temperatures, vacuum,
有宇宙幅射
and radiation of space.
但它中的一部分在被Щ氐降厍蛑後
And some of them were still alive and kicking
仍然生活虎
when they were brought back to Earth.
@些生物有更令人@的一面
Even more astonishing are these creatures,
它能800f年的假死B中d醒
awakened from a deathlike sleep of eight million years.
它曾被冰封在南O
They were frozen in the Antarctic ice
在人出F前好装偃f年就已存在
millions of years before our species even existed.
而且它依然活著
And they're still alive.
如果生命能受住毫拥奶空h境
If life can withstand the hardships of space
K且千年不死的
and endure for millennia,
那它就能乘坐著星H快
then it could ride the natural interplanetary transit system
囊世界到另一世界
from world to world.
很有可能 我的微生物先祖
It's a good bet that our microbial ancestors
就是@奶空降R
spent some time in space.
槭颤N我如此J椋
Why do we think so?
地球有45|年的v史
The Earth is four-and-a-half- billion-years old.
在它的Q生初期有一半的rg
For the first half of its lifetime,
都在被巨型小行星Z炸著
large asteroids were bombarding the planet
劫y每隔装偃f年就硪淮
every few million years.
最猛烈的n艨梢宰海洋蒸l
The most violent impacts vaporized the oceans
地表的岩石融化
and even melted the surface rock.
每一次如此巨大的n
Each such collision would have
都能星球上的生命全
completely sterilized the planet
K持m好浊年
for thousands of years.
但我幕石中得知
But we know from fossils in the rocks
菌早已在地球上生存
that bacteria were evolving on Earth
哪嵌蔚厍蛐纬傻脑缙诰鸵验_始
during this formative period.
那生命又是如何逃^@些劫y的呢？
So how could life have survived such a lethal series of blows?
任何一次巨大的小行星n舻厍r
Whenever one of those big asteroids
爆炸都形成大坑
hit the Earth, the explosion would blast out a crater,
装偃fK巨石入太空
launching millions of boulders into space.
S多石^中有菌存在
Many of those rocks carried living bacteria inside.
有些小生物就能像@由存在太空中
Some of the bugs would have survived in space,
而它留在地球上的同早已被烤焦了
while all those left behind on Earth would have been fried.
撞暨^後浊年
A few thousand years after each impact,
地球又冷s下
the Earth would have cooled down enough
水凝聚楹Ｑ
for water to condense into oceans.
地球又得m宜居住了
The planet would again be habitable.
c此同r 在太空中的大部分石^
Meanwhile, most of the rocks launched into space
正在@著太D
would have been orbiting the Sun.
它中的一部分重新c地球相遇
Some of them would encounter the Earth again,
像E石一舆M入地球大
reenter the atmosphere as meteorites,
⑺yУ恼滟F生命
and deliver their precious cargo of life
重新播⒌竭@行星上
to re-seed the planet...
如同Z方舟
like Noah's ark.
如果生命不能
What this means is that life doesn't have
像@慕^世天劫中重新_始的
to start over again from scratch after each catastrophe.
它能钠渌地方再硪淮
It can pick up where it left off.
r太系很年p
When the solar system was young,
金星可能更像地球
Venus was probably more like Earth,
有海洋 甚至有生命
with oceans and maybe even life.
金星 地球 火星都由於E石n
Venus, Earth, and Mars were all exchanging rocks
而在互相魉褪^
with each other, due to asteroid impacts.
地球上的生命有]有
Does life on Earth carry any traces
yе@些bh的星H迷航的索？
of interplanetary voyages made in the distant past?
槭颤N有些微生物能
Why is it that some microbes can survive
在烈的射c真空的太空中活著？
the intense radiation and vacuum of space?
@拥沫h境根本就不在地球上存在^
These conditions don't naturally exist on Earth.
也S@些小生物在告V我
Maybe those bugs are telling us
它的先祖装偃f年前_始
that their ancestors survived those same conditions in space,
就已是@釉谔空中活著
a few billion years ago.
既然我知道了微生物能通^石^
So we know that microbes can stow away in rocks
在行星之gw渡
and survive the voyage from planet to planet.
那有]有可能a星到a星？
But what about trip from star to star--
F更V的星系旅行？
an interstellar odyssey?
蒲公英
The dandelion.
有3000f年的v史
Around 30 million years ago,
它碛邪炎陨淼纳命信息鬟f出去的不同方式
it evolved another way to send its own message of life
那就是通^r空
through space and time.
每一N子都是一小惚
Each seedling is a little paratrooper,
它漂浮在空庵
floating on the wind,
上下浮沉 ふ乙安全之所
risking everything for a safe place to land.
上升饬髂馨阉У礁呖
Updrafts can carry them higher into the air.
蒲公英能穿越凳
A dandelion can travel dozens,
或者是蛋俟里
possibly hundreds of kilometers,
甚至能跨^高山
even crossing over mountain ranges.
M化⑺塑造成榫妙的w行器
Evolution has shaped it into an exquisite flying machine.
它的N子就是另一N方舟
The seed is another kind or ark,
_保物N得以存活
ensuring the survival of its species
乘Lh往安全之地
by riding the currents of the atmosphere to safe harbors.
每N子Y的DNA都藏著一故事
Each seed in its DNA carries a story,
那就是下一代蒲公英的特徵c命\
the character and destiny of the next dandelion--
生命通^}u自身而鞑コ鋈
life propagates by retelling its story.
那生命有]有可能
Is it possible that life could survive the journey
在a星到a星的旅行中存活下恚
from star to star?
a星之g的距x要比
The stars are about a million times farther apart
行星之g的距x多出一百f倍
from each other than are the planets.
距x是如此的bh 以至於要好装偃f年後
Space is so vast that it would take billions of years
地球的石^才抵_那Y
for a rock ejected from the Earth
然後c@另一wa星\D的行星相遇
to collide with a planet circling another star.
]有微生物能
Any stowaway microbes would never survive
在如此Lrg的宇宙幅射下存活
the cosmic radiation for that long.
但有一可行的方案
But there's a plausible scenario
可以F生命奶系向另一星系的鞑
for how life could spread from one solar system to another.
y河系的a星受引力的
The stars of the Milky Way are drawn by gravity
它在自己的巨大道中@著y河中心\行
in their own enormous orbits around its center.
比如我的太
Our Sun, for example,
每隔2|2千5百f年就完成一次道\行
takes some 225 million years to complete a single orbit.
在每次@y河系公D中
During each revolution around the galaxy,
太系穿越2到3
our solar system will pass through two or three
巨大的星H
gigantic interstellar clouds,
每星H都有好坠饽
each of them many light years across.
y河系是一巨大的星球工S
Galaxies are world-making machines.
我的y河中有超^100@拥拇笮托请
Our Milky Way has more than 100 of these vast clouds,
怏w和m埃在那Y聚集
a place where gas and dust condense
形成新的a星c行星
to form new stars and planets.
在y河的旅途中
In its travels through the Milky Way,
太不H由其行星相伴
our Sun is accompanied not only by its planets,
而且有狄匀f|的bh的彗星跟S
but also by a trillion distant comets.
太系穿^星Hr
When our solar system passes through an interstellar cloud,
巨大星的引力
the gravity of the massive cloud
恿俗钔拥腻缧
stirs up the outermost comets.
有些彗星被扔出到
Some comets will be hurled out
a星g的空g
into the space between the stars.
有些t被拉M了
Others will plunge inward...
直奔太的路
falling towards the Sun.
它中的一部分可能c行星相撞
And some of them may collide with the planets.
彗星以高速碰撞了多岩石的行星
The high-speed impact of a comet with a rocky planet
⒋罅康氖^入太空
will launch boulders like rockets into space.
如果@星球上正好有生命存在
If that planet should happen to be inhabited,
那N@S多的石^中就有乘客
many of those rocks will carry passengers--
活的微生物
living microbes.
浊年後
After thousands of years,
地球石^的碎K
fragments of the rocks ejected from Earth
像E石一勇湓谛律的行星上
can fall as meteors into the atmospheres of newborn planets
就在那星HY
in the interstellar cloud.
那些偷渡的微生物
If the stowaway microbes
如果正好遇到了液B水
should happen to come in contact with liquid water,
它就_始彤dK不嘌}u
they can revive and reproduce.
生命也S就是@
This may be how life comes barreling
M入另一荒的天地
into the barren places.
太也是由星聚集而成
The sun emerges from the cloud,
它把生命的N子
having scattered the seeds of life
散播在其它a星的新生世界中
among the newborn worlds of other stars.
@些新世界F在被生命所|及
Those new worlds, now touched by life,
然後x_它Q生的星
will then leave their birth cloud
拇颂旄饕环
and go their separate ways.
最K @些a星又把它
Eventually, their stars will carry them
У狡渌的星H那Y
through other interstellar clouds,
也S它又⑸⒉ド命到更多的新世界中
where they may seed still more new worlds.
想像一下 如果@拥倪^程在不同的星球之g重}
Imagine this process repeated from world to world,
每一次都把生命Ыo另一世界
each one bringing life to others.
生命就以@泳慢的式反鞑ラ_
Life would then propagate, like a slow chain reaction,
M整y河
through the entire galaxy.
生命也S就是如此降R地球
This could be how life came to Earth.
可我不能_定
We do not know for sure.
外面是否有像我一拥纳物？
Are there any beings out there like us?
他是否也在同拥}？
Do they ask the same questions?
他也害怕幔
Do they share our fears?
他是否也有英雄c髌妫
Do they have heroes and adventures?
如果他存在 又在哪Y？
If they do exist, where are they?
他又如何@示他的存在？
How might they make their presence known?
人是如何第一次宣炎约涸阢y河系的存在？
How did we first announce our presence to the galaxy?
1946年 二鸾Y束後的第二年
It was 1946, the year after the Second World War ended.
再生拥南胂窳
The vivid imaginations
就算是威斯的小f和巴克?_芩沟奶诫U
of HG Wells and Buck Rogers
它的狂也比不上
never cooked up a more fantastic experience
我的工程
than the Army engineers
在新晌髦葚R室Y值氖
at their laboratory in Belmar, New Jersey.
它槿祟_⒘
It opens up unlimited possibilities
星H探U的o限可能性
for interstellar experiment.
美的工程
American engineers
向月球l送了一束o波
bounced a beam of radio waves off the Moon,
K成功地zy到了它的回波
and were able to detect its echo.
他把@Q榇靼材扔
They called this experiment Project Diana.
@是由人l出的首次
It was the first interstellar message
星H信息鬟f
ever sent by our species...
那是一段起砗芄之的
an eerie, tolling bell.
只要l]一下o限的想像力
If one allows the imagination free reign,
o限的可能性涌F出
many future possibilities appear.
d人太空w船上
Spaceships, carrying passengers
它以每小r登в⒗锏乃俣刃旭r
it thousands of miles per hour,
我能有效地控制它
can be controlled
K且建立起通B接
and communication established
cw船上的乘客交
with their passengers,
因楝F在我已知道了
for we now know that the Earth's atmosphere
地球的大馐强梢员淮┩傅
can be penetrated.
物w以光速行Mr
Traveling at the speed of light,
只需要1秒
it takes just over one second
就能o波抵_月面
for a radio wave to reach the lunar surface.
但U散_淼牟面比月球更大
But the expanding wavefront is much bigger than the Moon.
大部分的波脑虑蚺赃^
Most of the wave passes right by it,
只有中央部位的波反回
but the central part gets bounced back.
^2.5秒的砘rg後
After a round-trip travel time of two and a half seconds,
波回到了地球
it hits our planet.
戴安娜鬏了
Project Diana transmitted
一B串的烈o波
a series of powerful radio waves--
每隔4秒l送1次
one every four seconds--
好比是我在"Ping"月亮
to "ping" the Moon.
ping:用y包能否通^IPfh到_特定主C
那些]有抵_月亮的波仍^m旅行
The parts that missed the Moon are traveling still.
@HH是_端
It was just the beginning.
二疳
After World War II,
美各地的台遍地_花
television stations cropped up all over the United States,
世界各地也同尤绱
and other parts of the world.
戴安娜l送的信息
The Project Diana message
FMV播、c雷_l送的信
and the FM radio, television and radar signals
在20世o中
of the 20th century
早已以光速向外四l送
all move outward at the speed of light.
@些信M成了巨大的一o波
These transmissions make up a vast sphere of radio waves,
在地球之外向四周U
expanding away from the Earth in all directions.
可以f 我的世界
You could say that our world
正在向外V播故事
is radiating stories.
我的祖先把吉伽美什的故事
Our ancestors etched the story of Gilgamesh
刻在泥板上
into clay tablets,
以此把髌媪鞯轿
sending that epic tale into the future.
我t是把故事Do波
We've encoded our stories in radio waves
l送到太空中去
and beamed them into space.
它每年要走1光年
They cover one light-year of distance--
也就是6f|英里
that's six trillion miles--
自乃被l送出去的那一刻起
for every year of time since they were sent.
人已像@酉蛱空l送信息
We've been sending our stories into space
超^70年了
for over 70 years.
最先l出的波
The leading edge of these signals
已M吡
has already washed over
其它a星的浊行星
thousands of planets of other stars.
如果@些星球上的文明
If any of these worlds are home
碛o望hR的
to a civilization with radio telescopes,
他可能已知道我在@Y
they could already know that we're here.
如果其他的世界也能虬l送
What if other worlds are sending
他的故事到太空中 又怎樱
their stories into space?
自1960年以 人一直在O
Since 1960, we've been listening
碜酝馓空的o信
for extraterrestrial radio signals
不^]有到什N像那拥|西
without hearing so much as a tolling bell.
不^我的研究^於零散
But our search has been sporadic
只局限於天空中的某部分
and limited to certain parts of the sky.
F在我知道
For all we know,
我也Se^了某些外星人的信
we may have just missed an alien signal,
因槲找的是e`的地c
looking in the wrong place
在e`的rg
at the wrong time.
我O的只是很小的一部分
We've only listened to a miniscule fraction
於我y河系的星球碚f
of the stars in our galaxy.
或S有其他的}
And there may be another problem...
我人哪承┓矫碚f
we are, to some extent,
是r代的囚徒
prisoners of our own moment in time
受困於我的科技水平
and the limits of our technology.
ocV播
Radio and television broadcasting
也S只是在人的科技l展史中
may be only a brief passing phase
一很蔚碾A段
in our technological development.
我O想著外星文明
When we imagine alien civilizations
也在用o望hRl送著信的r候
broadcasting signals with radio telescopes,
我又和那些
are we any different from earlier generations
O想著乘坐炮w到月球的先人有什N不同?
who imagined riding cannon shells to the Moon?
比人更先M的外星文明
Civilizations even slightly more advanced than ours
也S已l展到
may have already moved on
另外一N通模式了
to some other mode of communication,
一N我不知道
one that we have yet to discover
更o法想像的方式
or even imagine.
他的信息很有可能
Their messages could be
此刻就@在我的周
swirling around us, at this very moment,
可我不懂得怎N去捕@它
but we lack the means to perceive them,
就像我的祖先一
just as all of our ancestors,
在一多世o以前
up to a little more than a century ago,
人常察X不到
would have been oblivious to the most urgent radio signal
e的地方淼o呼救信
from another world.
有一更棘手的可能性
But there's another, more troubling possibility--
文明和生命w一
civilizations, like other living things,
由於自然的原因或者是暴力
may only live so long before perishing
或者是自行造成的
due to natural causes, or violence,
在生存^一段rg以後便消亡
or self-inflicted wounds.
不管怎 我已M力
Whether or not we ever make contact
L去接|外星文明
with intelligent alien life
@可能取Q於另一重要的}
may depend on a critical question.
一文明的勖有多L？
What is the life expectancy of a civilization?
恩西杜拉娜的年代
By the time of Enheduanna,
也就是人v史上最早出F借J的年代
the first person to ever get a writing credit,
r文明已存在超^了一千年
civilization was already more than 1,000 years old.
但今天 她那x煌的城市只是一堆荒的U墟
But today, her glorious city is a barren wasteland.
是哪Y出了差e？
What went wrong?
其中一重要的原因就是l生在美索不_平原的城邦之g的那些
One problem was the almost ceaseless warfare
o休止的
between the cities of Mesopotamia,
摧Я巳祟的成就
which continually destroyed their achievements.
ゴ蟮能功
They glorified military conquest
使它最K成榱奚品
and ultimately became its victims.
另一消亡的原因
Another cause of decline
是他的技g知R
was that their technical know-how
hh超^了他ψ匀坏睦斫
overran their understanding of nature.
巧妙的灌溉系y
The ingenious irrigation system that was the basis
是美索不_米ゴ笪拿鞯幕A
for the great civilizations of Mesopotamia
但也引l了一意想不到的Y果
had an unintended consequence--
每年水都^管道M入他的r田
the water channeled into their farmlands every year
水蒸l後有}留下
evaporated and left its salt behind.
^状人的rg後 e累下淼柠}
Over generations, the salt accumulated
f稼枯死
and began to kill the crops.
然後 在大s公元前2200年
And then, about 2,200 BC,
就在恩西杜拉娜的r代^後不久
not long after the time of Enheduanna,
碾y降R
disaster struck...
劫y一拥那旱砼R
a drought of truly epic proportions,
延m了好资年
lasting for many decades.
雨停了 f稼枯萎
rains stopped, crops withered,
遍地是荒c混y
and there was famine and anarchy.
U族入侵
Barbarians invaded.
S多城市的街道上都是死
The streets of many cities were littered with dead.
只有一N解
There could be only one explanation.
恩利 至高o上的神
Enlil, the supreme god,
他l怒了 因
was angry because one of his temples
他的一座寺R被摧
had been destroyed.
美索不_米人不知道
The people of Mesopotamia could not know
同拥那旱摧Я
that the same drought was crushing
埃及文明的曙光
the dawning civilizations of Egypt,
有希D、印度
Greece, India,
巴基斯坦、中
Pakistan and China.
地球上所有的神`
All the gods of the Earth
一定是槭颤N事情而l怒了
must have been really angry about something.
管有非凡的才A
For all their brilliance,
@些文明中的人
the people of those civilizations
]想^把他的vc
had no inkling they were experiencing
夂蛲蛔M起
abrupt climate change.
3000年後 夂蛲蛔
3,000 years later, the climate
同咏蹬R另一x煌的文明
would change abruptly for another glorious civilization,
@一次是在中美洲
this one in Central America.
在文明的峰r刻
At its peak,
雅文明消失了
the Mayan civilization perished,
被一系列的乾旱所
wiped out by a series of severe droughts
乾旱延m了一世o
over the course of a century.
我依然得
We still carry within us
@些已缃^文明的故事
the echoes of these extinct civilizations
留在了我的Z言c神Y
in our languages and our myths.
今天 人迎砹巳球文明的r代
Today, we have a single global civilization.
@一次能延m多久？
How long will it live?
文明的缃^有很多N方式
There are so many ways for a civilization to die.
我倪@一
Let's start with the ones
人Υo能榱Φ拈_始
that we probably wouldn't be able to do much about.
1000光年外的超新星爆l
That supernova is 1,000 light-years away.
它只要再近一c 比如f
If it were much closer, say...
距x地球少於30光年
less than 30 light-years from Earth,
宇宙射就切碎
its cosmic radiation would shred
地球大獾某粞醣Ｗo
the atmosphere's protective ozone layer
摧我的文明
and destroy our civilization.
幸\的是 距x我那N近的a星Y
Lucky for us, none of the stars close enough to harm us
起a在未淼装偃f年Y
are likely to go supernova
]有一w成超新星
any time in the next few hundred million years.
每隔一百f年左右
Every million years or so,
地球上有一座超大型火山爆l
a supervolcano erupts somewhere on Earth.
最近的一次是七f四千年以前
The last time it happened was 74,000 years ago,
在KT答Du上
on the island of Sumatra,
也就是今天的印度尼西
in what is now Indonesia.
它出的
It spewed hundreds of times more
岩石、火山灰和有毒怏w
rock, ash and toxic gas
比有d以淼娜魏我蛔火山都要超出百倍
than any single volcano in recorded history.
熔岩牡ぶ斜l出
The molten rock that erupted from Earth's crust
x_@火山口
left this caldera,
d延100公里
100 kilometers long,
@YF在形成了一湖
now filled with a lake.
多巴火山把超^600立方英里的碎石向天空
The Toba volcano sent more than 600 cubic miles of pulverized rock soaring skyward.
西L把火山灰У搅擞《
The westward wind carried the volcanic ash over India,
就像一K厚厚的毛毯那
where it fell out in a smothering blanket
覆w了整印度次大
over the subcontinent.
@次爆l地球的上哟獬M了硫
The eruption loaded the upper atmosphere with sulfur gases.
形成了全球性的F霾天
The result was a global haze
阻趿舜蟛糠值年光
that blocked most of the sunlight
照射到地面 K持m了至少5年
from reaching the surface for at least five years.
就好像是一延m了5年的天
It was like one five-year-long cloudy day.
@就是所^的"火山冬天"
This so-called "volcanic winter"
它似於"核冬天"  但是]有射
resembled a "nuclear winter," but without the radiation.
全球叵陆
Temperatures fell everywhere.
即使是在У^ 又参锒被鲎
Plants and animals froze even in the tropics,
死亡的更是不其
dying in enormous numbers.
但生命是B的
But life is hardy.
只有很少一部分物N遭到缃^
Only a few species were driven to extinction.
在印度中部生活的一位古人
One of our ancestors in central India
就在多巴火山爆l的前1年
sharpened this stone blade
把@K石^磨成了石刀
in the years before the Toba eruption.
而@一K石刀
And this blade
是人lF的十装咽刀中的一把
was one of dozens that were found
它就在火山灰上的那一油裂Y
in the soil layer above the volcanic fallout.
@f明做@些工具的人
This tells us that some toolmakers,
m然他就生活在直接受火山影的地^
even in the area directly affected by the volcano,
依然O法在@龃淖中生存下
managed to survive the cataclysm.
但r的全球人口
But the global human population
必定暴跌 然後又出F了回升
must have plummeted before rebounding.
如果明天就有@右龌鹕奖l
If an eruption like this were to happen tomorrow,
即使人能存下
our civilization would be brought to its knees,
我的文明也一蹶不振
although the human species would survive.
可以O想 我的科技在装倌赆
I can imagine that our technology of a few hundred years from now
可以我吸取
would allow us to siphon off
在火山即⒈l的r刻
the energy of a threatening supervolcano
具有威before it explodes.
我能把@些能量化榧河
We could then use that energy for our own purposes.
每隔那N装偃f年
About once every million years, a small asteroid
就有一w小行星碰撞地球
collides with the Earth,
造成似的破
causing a similar amount of devastation.
根我F有的科技
With our current science and technology,
人已知道如何避免小行星n撞
we already know how to prevent an asteroid impact.
我能提早的臧lF它的到
We would see it coming years in advance
K把航天w行器送到那Y
and could send a spacecraft there
⑺D移到一不造成害的道
to deflect it into a harmless orbit.
浊年後 也S我的科技
With the technology of a thousand years from now,
已l展到能我pp
we might even be able to mitigate the deadly effects
在地球附近爆l的超新星的影
of a nearby supernova on Earth's atmosphere.
但如果降R人的危U是悄o息的
But what happens when the danger to a civilization is invisible?
]人可以A 那又如何是好
When no one can see it coming?
^哥布之後
Beginning with Columbus,
W洲人不嗲致悦乐
the European invaders of the Americas
他yе自己也不知道的秘密武器
had a secret weapon that even they knew nothing about.
就是他yУ募菌c病毒
They were carrying bacteria and viruses
那是致命的疾病 比如天花
for deadly diseases, such as smallpox,
美洲的原住民奈唇佑|^
that the original Americans had never been exposed to.
W洲人以
The Europeans like to believe
是他的勇夂烷L利炮
that it was their valor and superior weapons
有越的文化他征服了新大
and culture that won them the New World.
但真正的征服者
The real conquistadors were
是比人跑得更快的病原w
the armies of the pathogens that raced on ahead
它感染K⑺懒嗽诒泵乐蕖⒅忻乐蕖⒛厦乐
to infect and kill nine out of ten of all the Indians
近九成的印第安人
of North, Central and South America.
新大的ゴ笪拿
The great civilizations of the New World
在入侵微生物的攻粝卤⒘
crumbled under the onslaught of invading microbes.
]有@支看不的
Without his invisible army,
科特斯和他的小夥伴根本]C征服新大
Cortez and those who followed might never have stood a chance.
如果文明走向自我 又怎樱
But what about civilizations that self-destruct?
我的w系是建立在
Our economic systems were formed when the planet
@星球的空 河流 海洋 地
and its air, rivers, oceans, lands,
似乎都用之不竭的假像之上
all seemed infinite.
他在人Q生之前
They evolved long before we first saw the Earth
早已走在M化的道路之上
as the tiny organism that it actually is.
全球w系都有一共同c
They're all alike in one respect...
那就是逐利而行
they're profit-driven,
因此 只P注眼前利益
and therefore, focused on short-term gain.
代主要的w系
The prevailing economic systems,
不管它是姓"社"是姓"Y」"
no matter what their ideologies,
一律缺乏仍诘C制肀Ｗo我的子O後代
have no built-in mechanisms for protecting our descendants
哪怕是100年都]有
of even 100 years from now,
更不要f一f年了
let alone, 100,000.
哪方面碚f 我做得比
In one respect, we're ahead
古代的美索不_米人更偏激
of the people of Ancient Mesopotamia.
和他不同的是 我知道自己在做什N
Unlike them, we understand what's happening to our world.
例如 人以地球在^去100f年Y未有的速度
For example, we're pumping greenhouse gases into our atmosphere at a rate not seen on Earth
向地球排放厥怏w
for a million years.
科W界的共R是
And the scientific consensus
人在夂蜃得不定
that we're destabilizing our climate.
然而 我的文明似乎Υ擞植灰槿
Yet our civilization seems to be in the grip of denial;
陷入了麻木不仁的境地
a kind of paralysis.
人知道的是一回事
There's a disconnect between what we know
做的又是另外一回事
and what we do.
能自已的行檫mh境的化
Being able to adapt our behavior to challenges
是人智慧的wF
is as good a definition of intelligence as any I know.
如果f高的智慧是我物N的苏I
If our greater intelligence is the hallmark of our species,
那我就好好利用它
then we should use it,
其它的物N都在利用它的特
as all other beings use their distinctive advantages--
碜自己的後代繁s昌盛
to help ensure that their offspring prosper,
它的z鞯靡粤
and their heredity is passed on,
@是自然界的基本w系 SM著人的生存
and that the fabric of nature that sustains us is protected.
然 人的智慧是不完美的
Human intelligence is imperfect, surely,
@就a生了很多新}
and newly arisen.
人很容易被甜言所惑 不知所措
The ease with which it can be sweet-talked, overwhelmed,
或是曲撵
or subverted by other hard-wired tendencies,
有r候假借理性硌谏w刃牡n
sometimes themselves disguised as the light of reason, is worrisome.
可如果智慧是我最大的
But if our intelligence is the only edge,
我就善用它
we must learn to use it better.
改M它
To sharpen it.
t解它的局限c不足
To understand its limitations and deficiencies.
像自然界的游镆
To use it as cats use stealth before pouncing.
不E用它的力量
As walking sticks use camouflage.
它成槿祟生存的工具
To make it the tool of our survival.
如果人能做到@一c
If we do this, we can solve
那N在未淼10f年Y
almost any problem we are likely to confront
一切困y都能迎刃而解
in the next 100,000 years.
F在 我淼搅
And now we've arrived at the place
古人粝胫械牟恍嘀地
where our ancient dreams of immortality
也是F代天文WP注的焦c
and modern astrophysics converge.
巨EA星系
Giant elliptical galaxies
它看上去有c像佛_里_州
are something like... Florida,
在那Y可能有著宇宙最古老的a星
where the oldest stars in the universe may be found.
@是一wt矮星
This is a red dwarf star,
比太更小更暗
smaller and fainter than our Sun.
t矮星是宇宙中盗孔疃嗟a星
Red dwarfs are by far the most plentiful stars in the cosmos.
它c太不一
Unlike the Sun, which is halfway through
太正於近100|年勖的中途
its 10-billion-year lifetime,
t矮星t可以樗的行星
red dwarfs will continue to provide light and warmth
提供光和岢^上f|年
to their planets for trillions of years.
@要比F在宇宙的年g
That's hundreds of times longer
要多出蛋俦
than the present age of the universe.
如果智能生命可以永a存在
What would intelligent beings do
他做些什N
if they had an eternity
硗卣顾於宇宙的t解？
to develop their understanding of the universe?
也S他能找到在宇宙_
Perhaps they would learn how to open shortcuts
r空隧道的方法
in the fabric of spacetime,
亩在不同的星系之g
to travel between galaxies
以比光速更快的速度旅行
faster than the speed of light.
也S他能造出全新的宇宙
Maybe they would create whole new universes
就像是g或科W的
as artistic or scientific experiments.
可F在 至少是在地球上
Of course no one, or at least nobody on Earth,
]人知道永生的人做什N
knows what the immortals might do.
只要l]一下o限的想像力
If one allows the imagination free reign.
可我呢？
But what about us?
我的未是怎樱
What is our own future?
宇宙的年v
What would the Cosmic Calendar
在下一140|年Y是什N幼樱
of the next 14 billion years look like?
如果最初的宇宙年v
If the original Cosmic Calendar
包含了宇宙Q生至今的所有rg
includes all of time from the birth of the universe
直到F在@一刻
until this very moment...
那N宇宙的年v
what would the Cosmic Calendar look like
在下一140|年Y是什N幼樱
for the next 14 billion years?
和^去的宇宙年v一致
Just as with the Cosmic Calendar of the past,
未砟v上的每月
every month the future calendar
都相於10|年
equals about a billion years;
每一天相於4千f年
every day, some 40 million.
科W使我可以Ay
Science makes it possible for us to foretell
未淼哪承┨煳氖录
certain astronomical events
即使它l生在想像不到的bh未
in the unimaginably distant future--
例如 太的死亡
the death of the Sun, for example.
在大s50|年後
In some five billion years,
@wa星耗M它的
our star will have exhausted its hydrogen--
那是它的核能碓
the nuclear fuel that powers it--
成橐活wt巨星
becoming a red giant.
@起砗茏人^望
I know that sounds depressing,
但如果人能l]出智慧
but if we apply our intelligence, our descendants
我在那bh未淼尼岽
of that distant future will have long departed
也S早已hx了太系@失落的世界
from the lost worlds of the Sun.
天缘
Who knows?
人的活砹颂多的
Human events entail too many variables,
有太多的不_定性
too many uncertainties,
很y做出θ祟未淼目WAy
to make scientific statements about our future.
但我依然粝
But we can still dream.
人的下一S金年代
The next golden age of human achievement
就_㈧堆矍按丝
begins here and now--
第二宇宙年的元旦
New Year's Day of the next cosmic year.
在最初的十分之一秒
In the first tenth of a second,
人人都P鬯we take the vision of the pale blue dot to heart,
Wc他人一同共享@世界
and learn how to share this tiny world with each other.
最後一台热C
The last internal combustion engine
被放M了博物^
is placed in a museum,
人於夂虻挠绊小以至於消失
as the effects of climate change reverse and diminish.
在未淼奈宸种一秒
A fifth of a second into this future
人不再因F而死去
people will stop dying from the effects of poverty.
地球F了完全的自o自足
The planet is now a completely self-sustaining,
成橐互通有o的大M
intercommunicating organism.
半秒^後
A half-second from now,
O地的冰帽_始
the polar ice caps are restored
恢偷19世o的水平
to the way they were in the 19th century,
夂更加睾鸵巳
and the forecast is mild and pleasant
在下一1分半RY
for the next cosmic minute and a half--
也就是4f年
40,000 years.
到了人已_始
By the time we are ready to settle
向最近的宜居星球殖民的r候
even the nearest other planetary systems,
世界已然大不同了
we will have changed.
@短的一段已然^了S多代人
The simple passage of so many generations
人改
will have changed us.
自然律改我
Necessity will have changed us.
我是善於mh境的N族
We are an adaptable species.
不是像我@拥娜说诌_
It will not be we who reach Alpha Centauri
半人R星座或者其它的a星星系
and the other nearby star systems
乘坐著星H方舟
on our interstellar arks.
那是一很像我的物N
It will be a species very like us,
比我更又]有我的缺c
but with more of our strengths and fewer of our weaknesses;
更有自信 目光h大
more confident, far-seeing,
更有能力和智慧
capable and wise.
m然我有NN弱c
For all our failings,
缺陷和局限性
despite our flaws and limitations,
但我人仍可Q得上ゴ
we humans are capable of greatness.
有什N粝朐谖@r代o法F的
What new wonders, undreamt of in our time,
也在下一代得以成真
will we have accomplished in another generation...
或是再下下一代
and another?
我@h泊的N族
How far will our nomadic species
是否要在下世o末
have wandered by the end of the next century,
或下一千禧年r^m漫[？
and the next millennium?
我bh的後代
Our remote descendants,
也S能安逸地活在其它的星球上
safely arrayed on many worlds
遍颜太系甚至更bh的地方
throughout the solar system and beyond,
他FY在共同的鹘y之下
will be unified by their common heritage,
共同P注著他的家@
by their regard for their home planet,
共同分享著知R
and by their knowledge that, whatever other life may be,
不管其它的生命是何N形式
the only humans in all the universe
宇宙中只有人是碜缘厍
came from Earth.
他把目光集聚在
They will gaze up and strain to find
天空中那the blue dot in their skies.
他@@
They will marvel at how vulnerable
我碛械力曾是何等的脆弱
the repository of all our potential once was,
我的早期是何等的U
how perilous our infancy,
我的起源是何等的卑微
how humble our beginnings,
我又跨越了多少的U阻
how many rivers we had to cross...
才找到了@l大道
before we found our way.